Every Occupational Accident Worker
每一位職業災害勞工的身士
They all have a story of their own and their destiny.
都有一個屬於他們自身與命運拼博的故事
Labor laws are so much today
勞動法今如此多
In the end occupational accident workers can
到底職災勞工可從事業單位
What should be covered by employer or labor insurance, etc.
雇主或勞工保險等獲得什應保障
Kaohsiung City Government Labor Bureau for assistance
高雄市政府勞工局為協助
A worker friend who suffered an occupational accident
遭遇職災的勞工朋友
Simple and fast instant instant self-rights
簡單快速的瞬解自身權益
Filming a series of occupational accident workers rights videos
拍攝一系列職災勞工權益影片
It is hoped that in an easy-to-understand way,
希望籍由淺顯易懂方式讓民眾面臨職災時
Can know how to fight for relevant labor rights
能夠知道如何爭取相關的勞動權益
so-called occupational disaster
所謂的職業災害
refers to the labor caused by the workplace
是指勞工因勞動場所
Work activities and other reasons for performing duties
作業活動及其他因執行職務的原因
Including commuting and public travel
包含上下班及公出途中
Sickness, injury, disability or death caused by
所引起的疾痛丶傷害、失能或死亡
Classification of occupational hazards
職業災害的分類
- Occupational injury in the course of performing duties
一執行職務相關的過程中所發生的職業傷害
2. Risk factors of long-term exposure to work
二長期暴露於工作中之危險因子
causally related to the injury
與傷病具有相當因果關條
leading to occupational diseases
進而導致職業疾病
You can apply for an occupational disease ship through
可透過職業傷病防治中心申請職業病艦定
Labor is always the most important part of urban development
勞工永遠是都市發展過程中最重要的一環
Since the promulgation of the Labor Standards Act in 1974, Taiwan has
台灣自1974年勞動基準法公佈後
A series of special laws have been formulated
持續訂定了一系列的專法
In order to improve working conditions and protect the rights and interests of workers
籍以改善勞動條件與保障勞動者權益
Improve the occupational disaster prevention system
使職災預防制度更加完善
But in the unfortunate event of an occupational accident
但若不幸發生職業災害
About your labor rights and resources to seek help
關於自身的勞動權益與可尋求協助之資源
will be the key to your return to work
將會是您重返職場的主要關鍵
I will always remember that day
我永遠記得那一天
It's Father's Day on August 8th
剛好是8月8號父親節
I do stamping work
我是作沖壓成形工作的
At that time I remember that I was feeding
那時候我記得我正在送料
I don't know why
結果不知道為什麼
The punch suddenly becomes a continuous punch
衝床突然變成連續衝壓
can not stop
停不下來
Because I can't get my hand out in time
我的手因為來不及抽出來
so caught
就被這樣夾住了
Later they said it was because the punch machine was
後來他們說是因為沖床機合
Caused by loose screws of clutch parts
離合器的零件螺絲松脫引起的
But it's too late to say that now
但現在說那些都來不及了
To assist with occupational disasters
為了協助因職業災害
causing family dysfunction
造成家庭功能失調
or working families with circumstances in their lives
或生活上出現因境的勞工家庭
Immediate access to appropriate welfare services resource intervention and support
能即時獲得適當的福利服務資源介入與支持
Kaohsiung City Government Labor Bureau in cooperation with the Ministry of Labor
高雄市政府勞工局配合勞動部
Continue to promote the active service plan for occupational accident labor cases
特續推動職業災害勞工個案主動服務計畫
Set up a single service window
設立單一服務窗口
Occupational Disaster Case Manager for Professional
職業災害個案管理員進行專業
One-to-one service
一對一服務
Provide free complete rights information for workers with occupational accident
免費提供職災勞工完整的權益資訊
Combine labor benefits and social welfare system and other related resources
結合勞工福利及社會福利系統等相關資源
to build a complete safety network
以建構完善的安全網絡
Implement the protection of labor rights
落實勞工的權益保障
Accompanying workers and families through the difficulties of life
陪伴勞工及家庭度過人生的難關
I do this kind of traditional manufacturing
我做這種傳統製造業的
Where can I know what should be called the Laoji law?
哪裡會懂什應叫勞基法
So when I got hurt
所以那時候我一受傷
The only thought in my head is
我腦子裡唯一的想法就是
gone
去了了啊
how should i take care of my family
我要怎應照顧我的家庭
The kids are still young
小孩子也都還小
when i was in the hospital
那時候我在醫院那段時間
The old pavilion also came once
老閣也有來過一次
It felt a bit
那時候感覺就有點
It seems that I don't want to go back
好像是要我不要回去了
I really don't know what to do
我真的不知道要怎應辦
Fortunately, the social worker at the hospital is very kind
還好醫院的社工很好心
Tell me you can go to our Kaohsiung City Labor Bureau for help
告訴我可以去找我們高雄市勞工局幫忙
I just want to say that otherwise, I'm desperate, let's try it out.
我就想說不然走投無路了來試看看好了
Later, the Department of Labor hired a case manager to help me.
後來勞工局有請個案管理員來幫我
Only then did I slowly know
那時候我才慢慢知道
There are subsidies available
原來還有補助可以領
What about sick leave?
連什麼公傷病假
Work rights are stipulated
工作權益都有規定
The point is that the boss can't get hurt because of my job
重點就是老闆不能因為我工作受傷
Just ask me to quit
就隨便叫我離職
In the end, it was the occupational disaster
最後也是職災個管員幫我申請勞資協商
Otherwise, how can I do it alone?
不然我一個人哪有辦法
According to my country's current labor standards law
根據我國現行勞動基準法規定
When a worker is injured or suffers from an occupational disease
當勞工受傷或罹患職業病時
There are four main types of expenses that employers should compensate for
雇主應補償的費用主要有四大項
Include medical reimbursement at the time of medical treatment
包括醫療時的醫療補償
Wage compensation for inability to work during medical treatment
醫療期間無法工作的工資補償
Diagnosed by the hospital according to the degree of disability
經醫院診斷依其失能程度
One-time disability compensation
一次性給予的失能補償
and funeral expenses for death due to occupational accident
以及因職災身故之喪葬費
and one-time compensation for death of survivors
與一次性給予遺屬的死亡補償
The content of the labor base law is also clearly defined
勞基法內容也明定了
Compensation protection and right to work protection
受領補償保障及工作權保障
Protects workers during medical treatment
保障了勞工於醫療期間
Employers may not dismiss without cause
雇主不得無故解雇
and the rights to receive compensation can be exercised within two years
與二年內可行使受領補償之權益
Seriously
講真的
I was actually worried at first about going to the labor office for help
我其實一開始很擔心去找勞工局幫忙
It seems that it will become the feeling that I want to tear my old pavilion apart
好像是會變成要跟我老閣撕破險的感覺
I learned later
後來才了解
Lao Ge and staff
老閣跟員工
have their own rights and obligations
本來就各自有自己的權利和義務
We work so hard every day for our family
我們每天為了家庭這樣辛苦的打拼
but was injured at work
但是卻因為工作而受傷
This kind of thing doesn't matter if it's your own life
這樣的事情不管是對自己的人生
or for family
還是對家庭來說
It's a big blow
都是很大的打擊
Ho Plus provides complete occupational disaster protection in the government
好加在政府提供完整的職災保障
Let me get up slowly
讓我能慢慢的再爬起來
Therefore, regarding the rights and interests
所以關於職災勞工應有的權益
I really don't know
不了解真的不行
In order to effectively implement the laws related to labor conditions
為了有效落實勞動條件相關法律的實施
and assist workers
並協助勞工
Protect your rights against theft in accordance with relevant labor laws
依據相關勞動法令保障自身權盜
Accident workers can call the Kaohsiung City Government Labor Bureau
職災勞工可以撥打高雄市政府勞工局
Labor-based law service line
勞基法服務合專線
ext 232, 233, 234
分機232、233、234
Or go directly to the Labor Conditions Section on the 7th floor for consultation
或直接到7樓勞動條件科進行諮詢
in addition
另外
If there is a need for labor dispute mediation
如有勞資爭議調解需求
You can also contact the Complaint Service
也可親洽一樓申訴服務中心申請調解
Our work is mainly to ensure that both employers and employees
我們的工作主要是為了要確保勞資雙方
in accordance with the Labor Standards Act
都能依照勞動基準法的規定
Especially the part of occupational accident compensation
尤其是職業災害補償的部分
When an employer or a worker friend does not understand this part
當雇主或勞工朋友因為不了解這部分
when the right to lose
而失去應有的權益時
For workers who suffer from occupational accidents
對於遭遇職災的勞工朋友來說
Undoubtedly a worrisome
無疑是一種雪上加霜
Many families are even caught in the situation because of this
很多家庭甚至因此而陷入了因境
The Kaohsiung City Government Labor Bureau
那高雄市政府勞工局
A lot of effort has been made in this part
在這一部分做了很多的努力
Whether it is the establishment of a single service window
不管是單一服務窗口的建立
or various counseling services
還是各項的輔導服務
If there are labor friends who need balls
如果有需球的勞工朋友
When you encounter related problems
當您遭遇到相關問題時
You can come to us directly
都可以直接來找我們
Let us assist you
讓我們來協助您
Can overcome difficulties and return to work
可以渡過困境重返職場
either employer or worker
無論是雇主或勞工
When in doubt about the relevant laws
當對於相關法令有疑義
or unfamiliarity with litigation procedures, etc.
或對訴訟程序不熟悉等相關問題
The Labour Office has also hired lawyers from the Legal Aid Foundation.
勞工局也特別聘請法律扶助基金會律師
Provide free consulting services
提供免費的諮詢服務
In addition, according to relevant laws and regulations
另外依相關法律規定
When a labor dispute cannot be mediated through
當勞資爭議經調解不成需提起訴訟時
Labor friends with financial difficulties
資力上有困難的勞工朋友
You can also apply for legal and living expenses support separately
也可另外申請法律及生活費用扶助
We have met many labor friends who suffered occupational accidents
我們遇過很多遭遇職業災害的勞工朋友
Worried about getting to this part of the lawsuit in the beginning
在一開始都很擔心走到訴訟這一部分
Many people gave up their rights because of this
許多人就因此放棄了自身的權利
What a pity
非常可惜
because in fact
因為事實上
Occupational injuries and diseases of workers in Taiwan
我們台灣現在勞工職業傷病
death compensation system
死亡補償制度
insured workers
有加保的勞工
Occupational Accident Compensation Liability under the Labor Standards Act
可依據勞動基準法職災補償責任
And labor insurance regulations Occupational Accident Insurance Liability
以及勞工保險條例 職災保險責任
to claim related rights
來主張相關的權益
uninsured people
未加保的民眾
Occupational Accident Labor Protection Act
則有職業災害勞工保護法
to provide relevant guarantees
來提供相關的保障
The Kaohsiung City Government also has measures
高雄市政府還有職業災害慰問金的辦法
That is to say
也就是說
Rights and Compensation for Occupational Accident Workers
對於職災勞工的相關權利及補償
At present, there are clear and sound legal provisions
在現在已經有很明確跟健全的法律規定
Based on the litigation costs that many labor friends are worried about
基至很多勞工朋友所擔心的訴訟費用
and living expenses during the litigation
以及訴訟期間的生活費
In fact, as long as you qualify
其實只要符合資格
Anyone can apply
都可以來申請
By Kaohsiung City Government Labor Bureau
由高雄市政府勞工局
Lawyer consulting services provided
所提供律師諮詢服務
and assistance with referral proceedings
以及轉介訴訟的協助
Helping you get the labor rights you deserve
幫助您得到應有的勞工權益
Last but not least
最後要提醒您的是
We are practical
我們在實務上
Workers who often encounter occupational accidents
經常遇到遭遇職業災害的勞工朋友
because I don't understand
因為不了解
leading to the execution of a so-called settlement with the employer
導致跟雇主簽立所謂的和解書
This may actually lead to subsequent
這其實可能導致在後續
Loss of interest in the relevant application
相關申請的權益喪失
Therefore, special reminder
因此要特別提醒
If you don't understand
如您不了解
You are also welcome to visit the Kaohsiung City
也歡迎到高雄市政府勞工局來尋求專業的諮詢
According to the 108 Occupational Safety and
依據108年勞動部職業安全衛生署之
Labor inspection statistics annual report shows
勞動檢查統計年報顯示
The type of disaster that was caught and
被夾被捲之災害類型約佔總數12.55%比例
Kaohsiung City Government Labor Bureau
高雄市政府勞工局
Continue to comply with the Occupational Safety and Health Act
持續依職業安全衛生法
Intensified inspections on the stipulated working conditions
所規定之勞動條件上加強檢查
Beyond advocacy and prevention
宣導及預防以外
In the event of an occupational disaster that no one wants to see
在所有人都不樂意所見的職災事件發生時
Provide professional fast
提供專業快速
and complete service resources
以及完整的服務資源
Help our labor friends step by step
幫助我們的勞工朋友一步步的
Through occupational accident labor cases
經由職業災害勞工個案
Assistance with proactive service programs
主動服務計畫的協助
A smooth return to work
順利重返職場
Kaohsiung City Government Labor Bureau
高雄市政府勞工局
Invite you to come and learn
邀請您一起來了解
Labor rights and interests that are closely related to you
與您息息相關的勞動權益
Every occupational accident worker
每一位職業災害勞工的身上
They all have a story of their own and their destiny.
都有一個屬於他們自身與命運拼博的故事
so many labor laws
勞動法令如此多
In the end occupational accident workers can
到底職災勞工可從事業單位
What is covered by employer or labor insurance, etc.
雇主或勞工保險等獲得什麼保障
Kaohsiung City Government Labor Bureau for assistance
高雄市政府勞工局為協助
A worker friend who suffered an occupational accident
遭遇職災的勞工朋友
Simple and fast airing of self-rights
簡單快速的晾解自身權益
Filming a series of occupational accident workers rights videos
拍攝一系列職災勞工權益影片
It is hoped that in an easy-to-understand way,
希望籍由淺顯易懂方式讓民眾面臨職災時
Can the dog know how to obtain relevant labor rights and interests
能狗知道如何事取相關的勞動權益
so-called occupational disaster
所謂的職業災害
refers to the labor caused by the workplace
是指勞工因勞動場所
Work activities and other reasons for performing duties
作業活動及其他因執行職務的原因
Including commuting and public travel
包含上下班及公出途中
Illness, injury, disability or death of the induced leg
所引腿的疾病丶傷害、失能或死亡
Classification of occupational hazards
職業災害的分類
- Occupational injury in the course of performing duties
一執行職務相關的過程中所發生的職業傷害
2. Risk factors of long-term exposure to work
二長期暴露於工作中之危險因子
causally related to the injury
與傷病具有相當因果關條
leading to occupational diseases
進而導致職業疾病
You can apply for an occupational disease ship through
可透過職業傷病防治中心申請職業病艦定
social insurance system
社會保險制度
a modern social security system
是一種現代的社會保障制度
by the power of the government
籍由政府的力量
formulate relevant legal norms
訂定相關的法律規範
Involve people in various types of insurance
讓人民參與各種保險
Prepare for various social risks in advance
預先為各種社會風險作準備
of which
而其中
Occupational Accident Insurance
職業災害保險
It provides a perfect guarantee for the occupational safety of workers
則為勞工在職業安全上提供了完善的保障
My husband works in formwork
我先生是從事板模工作的
I heard from his colleague
我聽他同事說
that day he was locking the screws of the die
那天他正在鎖板模的螺絲時
Due to limited space on site
因為現場的位置有限
There are some screws to lock which is difficult for one person to handle
有一些螺絲要鎖一個人很難處理
He had asked another nearby colleague to help
他原本有請另一位附近的同事幫忙一下
But that person is busy because he also has work at hand
但是那個人因為手上也有工作在忙
There is no way to help him right away
折以沒有辦法馬上幫他
My husband had to continue to lock those screws by himself.
我先生只好一個人繼續去鎖那些螺絲
It's been about half an hour.
過了差不多半小時左右吧
On the third floor, there is a worker who is making a window.
三樓剛好有一個作窗的工人正在施工
He suddenly heard several loud banging noises in a row.
他就突然聽到連續好幾聲很大聲的撞擊聲
So he ran over to see
結果他跑過去一看
My husband has fallen to the ground
我先生已經掉下來倒在地上了
Many working friends are the breadwinners of the family
很多勞工朋友都是家庭的經濟支柱
So when a job disaster occurs
因此當職災發生時
The family economy will soon be in trouble
家庭經濟馬上就會陷入困境
And occupational accident insurance pays at this time
而職災保險給付在這時候
Relevant payment resources can be provided in a timely manner
就可以適時的提供相關給付資源
Assisting workers with occupational disasters and
協助職災勞工與其家庭渡過因境
Howan's current occupational accident insurance benefits
合灣現行的職災保險給付
Mainly divided into cash payment
主要分為現金給付
Two ways of payment in kind
與實物給付二種方式
Then according to the individual status of the worker
再依據勞工個別的狀兄
Provide corresponding payment items
提供對應的給付項目
At that time, the hospital notified the labor bureau
那時候醫院有通報勞工局
An occupational disaster case manager volunteered to assist us
有一位職災個案管理員主動協助我們
Honestly
老實說
We do not have labor insurance
我們並沒有保勞保
Wherever there is a lack of work, we will do it
都是哪裡有缺工我們就去做
So you don't know until after it happened
所以事情發生後才知道
The current law restricts uninsured workers
現在的法律對沒有加保的勞工
There are also related grants and allowances
也有提供相關的補助和津貼
Luckily, there's an Occupational Disaster Case
還好有勞工局的職災個案管理員來幫忙
let us solve
讓我們晾解到
It turns out that the government has provided so many resources to use
原來政府有提供這麼多資源可以運用
Otherwise, I really don't know what to do.
不然那時真的不知道該怎應辦才好
In order to provide workers with better protection
為了能讓勞工朋友獲得更完善的保障
Occupational Accident Labor Protection Act
職業災害勞工保護法
Labor friends who will also not add labor insurance for some reason
也將因故末加勞保的勞工朋友
Included in the coverage of occupational accident insurance benefits
納入職災保險給付的保障範疇
Provide uninsured labor friends
提供未加保的勞工朋友
occupational sickness living allowance
包括職業疾病生活津貼
Disability Living Allowance
失能生活津貼
Vocational Training Living Allowance
職業訓練生活津貼
Appliance subsidy
器具補助
Nursing allowance
看護補助
family allowance
家屬補助
Disability allowance without labor insurance
未加勞保失能補助
Add labor insurance death benefit
末加勞保死亡補助
and occupational disaster subsidy programs such as auxiliary facilities subsidy
以及輔助設施補助等等的職災補助項目
For laborers based in Kaohsiung City
對於設籍高雄市的勞工朋友
Kaohsiung City Government also has
高雄市政府也訂有
Kaohsiung City Labor and Occupational Accident Consolation Payment Measures
高雄市勞工職業災害慰間金發放辦法
Come to help the families of workers who are disabled due to occupational accidents
來共同協助職災失能的勞工家屬
return to normal life
回復正常的生活
Actually, I think a lot of people are like me
其實我覺得很多人跟我一樣
Didn't read the book
沒讀什應書
Go online to see what the law says
要去上網啊看什麼法律規定的
really no way
真的是沒辦法
So I would suggest saying
所以我會建議說
If you have friends who have needs like me
如果有跟我一樣有需求的朋友
Just go to the labor office.
就是去找勞工局就對了
As I learned this time with the help of a professional disaster case manager
像我這次在職災個案管理員的幫忙之下才了解
I am very grateful to the government for taking care of us uninsured workers
很感謝政府有照顧我們這些沒有加保的勞工
So let's still apply for some
所以讓我們還是有申請到了一些
like a caregiver grant
像是看護的補助
Disability Living Allowance
失能生活津貼
And the incapacitated consolation allowance issued by our Kaohsiung City Government
還有我們高雄市政府發的失能慰間金
deeply appreciated
真的很感謝
Generally speaking
一般來說
Items covered by occupational accident insurance
職災保險給付的項目
Included can be used to pay for outpatient clinics
包括可用於支付門診
and medical benefits for hospitalization
及住院費用的醫療給付
When you are unable to work due to treatment
因治療中無法工作且未取得原有薪資時
Claimable Injury Benefit
可請領的傷病給付
In addition, there are losses to pay
另外還有失能給付
and death benefit
以及死亡給付
Occupational disasters for farmers and fishermen
而針對農漁民的職業災害
There are also related occupational accident
也都有相關的職災保險給付可以請領
people in need
有需要的民眾
You can contact the relevant travel agency to consult
都可以聯繁相關承游單位來諮詢
Modern people can generally agree with insurance planning
現代的人已普遍都能認同保險規劃
The concept of a rainy day
未雨網繆的概念
Started on January 1, 1998
在民國98年1月1日開始
Implement the labor insurance annuity system
實施勞保年金制度
Three benefits in disability old age and death
在失能老年及死亡三種給付
More ways to receive annuity every month
更增加了可以每個月領年金的方式
old age pension
也就是老年年金
Disability Annuity
失能年金
Three types of benefits and survivors' annuity
和遺屬年金三種給付
So there is labor insurance annuity
所以有了勞保年金
Labor friends will get better protection of rights and interests
勞工朋友將獲得更完善的權益保障
don't believe it easily
千萬不要輕易相信
The person who takes the initiative to help you say
主動來幫您說要代辦保險給付的人
These are the so-called labor insurance scalpers
遺些就是所謂的勞保黃牛
in a deceptive way
用一種誘騙的方式
To handle payment application procedures
來代辦給付申請手續
Then take high commissions
然後抽取高額佣金
This is very unreasonable for your rights
這對您的權益來說非常的不合理
So call on labor friends in need
所以呼籲有需求的勞工朋友
through the consultation line
可以透過諮詢專線
With us Kaohsiung City Government Labor Bureau
與我們高雄市政府勞工局
Or contact our labor insurance bureau
或是我們勞保局聯繫
We have professional staff to serve you
我們有專業的人員可以為您提供服務
For labor friends with consulting needs
對於有諮詢需求的勞工朋友
Ministry of Labor and Kaohsiung City Government
勞動部及高雄市政府
There are professional service windows
都設有專業的服務窗口
About the Occupational Accident Labor Protection Act
關於職業災害勞工保護法
The various allowances and subsidies stipulated
所訂定的各項津貼與補助間題
You can consult by phone
您可以電話諮詢
Or contact the Occupational Safety and Health
或親洽勞動部職業安全衛生署
And various application information about labor insurance benefits
而關於勞工保險給付的各項申請資訊
You can contact the General Administration of Labor Insurance of the Ministry of Labor
則可以洽詢勞動部勞工保險局總局
Or Kaohsiung City Office and Kaohsiung City Second Office
或是高雄市辦事處及高雄市第二辦事處
Disability related to occupational accident
有關職災失能
or part of the death benefit application
或死亡慰間金申請的部分
Inquiry from the Occupational Rehabilitation
可治勞工局職業重建科洽詢
Phone 07-8124613
電話07-8124613
ext. 523-527
轉分機523-527
Every occupational accident worker
每一位職業災害勞工的身上
They all have a story of their own and their destiny.
都有一個屬於他們自身與命運拼博的故事
so many labor laws
勞動法令如此多
In the end occupational accident workers can
到底職災勞工可從事業單位
What is covered by employer or labor insurance, etc.
雇主或勞工保險等獲得什麼保障
Kaohsiung City Government Labor Bureau for assistance
高雄市政府勞工局為協助
A worker friend who suffered an occupational accident
遭遇職災的勞工朋友
Simple and fast airing of self-rights
簡單快速的晾解自身權益
Filming a series of occupational accident workers rights videos
拍攝一系列職災勞工權益影片
It is hoped that in an easy-to-understand way,
希望籍由淺顯易懂方式讓民眾面臨職災時
Be able to know how to fight for relevant labor rights
能夠知道如何爭取相關的勞動權益
so-called occupational disaster
所謂的職業災害
refers to the labor caused by the workplace
是指勞工因勞動場所
Work activities and other reasons for performing duties
作業活動及其他因執行職務的原因
Including commuting and public travel
包含上下班及公出途中
Sickness, injury, disability or death caused by
所引起的疾痛丶傷害、失能或死亡
Classification of occupational hazards
職業災害的分類
- Occupational injury in the course of performing duties
一執行職務相關的過程中所發生的職業傷害
2. Risk factors of long-term exposure to work
二長期暴露於工作中之危險因子
causally related to the injury
與傷病具有相當因果關條
leading to occupational diseases
進而導致職業疾病
You can apply for occupational disease identification
可透過職業傷病防治中心申請職業病鑑定
the first time i saw lobule in the hospital
我第一次在醫院見到小葉的時候
Found out he was very young in his 20s
發現他非常年輕才20幾歲
Xiaoye was originally a delivery driver in a material company.
小葉他原本是在一間材料公司從事送貨司機的工作
It's hard work, the pay is not high
很辛苦薪水也不高
But because my baby was just born
但是因為自已的小孩剛出生
The wife must take care of the child at home
太太必須要先在家帶小孩
So he has been working hard to support his family
所以他一直很努力的工作養家
As a result, on the way to work one day
結果在一天上班的途中
Hit by an inverse locomotive
被一輛逆向的機車撞上
Injury caused by lumbar disc herniation
導致了腰椎椎間盤突出的傷害
The throbbing pain that comes with the swelling
那接腫而來的抽痛感
Make him so painful that he can't walk
讓他痛到無法行走
Even in the middle of the night will be woken up in pain
甚至晚上睡到一半也會被痛醒
It took a big hit in his mood and family life.
讓他的情緒跟家庭生活都受到了很大的打擊
I really didn't know what to do at the time
我那時候真的不知道該怎應辦
The constant pain makes it almost hard for me to think too much
持續的疼痛讓我幾乎很難思考太多東西
Even walking is a big problem for me
就連走路對我來說都是很大的間題
Later, a supervisor from the labor bureau took the initiative to contact me.
後來勞工局的個管員有主動跟我聯繫
In addition to explaining some related rights and interests to me
除了跟我解說一些相關的權益以外
And slowly began to explain something to me
也慢慢的開始跟我說明一些
About the process and method of career reconstruction
關於職業重建的流程跟方式
That's when I knew
那時候我才知道
It turns out that the government has many resources for career reconstruction
原來政府有提供許多職業重建的資源
Assist workers in occupational disasters to return to the workplace smoothly
協助職災勞工可以順利重返職場
Xiaoye's situation was really urgent in life at first.
小葉的狀況一開始在生活上真的蠻緊急的
Originally, the parents could barely help.
原本父母親還可以勉強接濟一下
But the baby was born soon
但是小孩出生不久
Parents also have debt problems
父母親也因為有債務問題
house under foreclosure
房子遭到法拍
Therefore, there is an immediate need for emergency assistance in the economy.
所以經濟上立即就有急難救助的需要
In order to make Xiao Ye feel at ease first
那為了要讓小葉先安心
Therefore, we first assisted in reporting the services
所以我們先協助通報了社會局的高風險弱勢家庭的服務
And Dan Referral Social Welfare Resources
並旦轉介社會福利的資源
Temporary emergency assistance
提供了暫時的急難數助
Gradually stabilize the economy of the lobular family
漸漸的對小葉家庭的經濟達到穩定的作用
The next step is in the medical process of the lobule.
接下來就是在小葉的醫療過程中
We also started planning for functional rehabilitation services
我們同時也開始進行職能複健服務的規劃
Because we know that the current condition can be treated with surgery
因為我們了解到目前的狀況是可以經過手術來治療的
Therefore, post-operative rehabilitation and work-intensive assistance
因此手術後的複健以及工作強化的協助
will be a critical part of returning to work
會是重返職場很關鍵的一部分
Occupational disaster occupational reconstruction is mainly divided into
職災職業重建主要分為
social rehabilitation, functional rehabilitation
社會復健，職能復健
and the three major parts of career rebuilding
以及 職業重建三大部分
The purpose of social rehabilitation is to protect
社會復健其目的在於為了保障
Minimum living conditions for workers with occupational injuries and illnesses
職業傷病勞工之最低生活條件
with the goal of restoring the social life function before the injury
並以恢復其傷病前之社會生活功能為目標
Special Committee by Case Manager
特委由個案管理員
Yutani utilizes county and city resources
結谷運用縣市資源
Provide occupational accident workers with
提供職災勞工關於權益諮詢保障
Legal Assistance, Labour Disputes Office, Family Services and Medical Care
法律協助丶勞資爭議協處、家屬服務及醫療
Welfare resource links and more
福利資源連結等等
Functional rehabilitation is to
而職能復健則是為了讓
Workers who suffer from occupational injuries can get effective treatment
遭遇職業傷病勞工能狗獲得有效的治療
Early recovery of pre-injury employment status and return to work
及早恢複傷病前之就業狀況及重返職場
Therefore, the committee will appoint a
因此會委由醫療單位來辦理醫療復健
Work ability assessment, work intensive training
工作能力評估、工作強化訓練
and return to work assistance
以及重返職場協助等等
Form for Workers with Disability Certificate
針對領有身障證明的職災勞工朋表
Kaohsiung City Government Labor Bureau Fraternity Skills Training Center
高雄市政府勞工局博愛技能訓練中心
Career Rebuild Services will be available
職業重建 服務將可以提供
Vocational Counseling Assessment, Vocational Training, Employment Services
職業輔導評量，職業訓練，就業服務
Service projects such as job redesign and entrepreneurial counseling
職務再設計以及創業輔導等等的服務項目
Surgery completed and medical rehabilitation for some time
手術完成並接受醫療復健了一段時間
some time to recover
有比較恢複的時候
The manager helped me
個管員有協助我
Arrange the work of our hospital to strengthen the training of the center
安排我醫院的工作強化中心表作訓練
Initially the therapist assessed my work situation needs
一開始治療師有先評估我的工作狀況需求
Follow me on my current recovery
跟我目前的恢複情況
A training plan is then drawn up and explained
然後再擬定並說明了訓練計畫
Then start working on things like the core muscles
然後就開始安排像是核心肌群
And basic training such as lower limb muscle strength training
以及下肢的肌力訓練等較為基礎的訓練
Then gradually add some work simulation training, etc.
接下來漸進式的加入一些工作模擬訓練等等
I'm actually a bit lucky
我其實有一點是比較幸運的是
The boss of the company is willing to help me adjust my position
公司老闆願意幫我調整職務
Because the original delivery job will require heavy lifting
因為原本的送貨工作會需要搬重物
Not good for the recovery of my spine
對我脊椎的復原比較不利
So there is a job to help me adjust to the quality inspection.
所以就有幫我調整到品檢的工作
It just takes longer to sit
只是坐的時間會比較久
Low back pain after sitting for a long time
坐久了仍有腰部疼痛的問題
After the therapist found out, he went to our company to see the working environment
那治療師知道後有到我們公司去看了一下工作環境
Assisted me with the application to make a work desk and high chair that suits me
協助我申請製作了適合我的工作桌跟高腳椅
It really helped me a lot at work
這對我在工作上真的有很大的幫助
When our disaster worker friends came here
當我們的職災勞工朋友來到這理的時候
We usually do a job analysis and competency assessment first
我們通常會先作工作分析及能力評估
Then set up a training plan for the part that is not yet up to the job
再來針對還無法勝任工作的部分設定訓練計畫
Usually start with job fitness training
一般會先從工作適能訓練開始
such as increasing joint mobility and muscle strength
像是加強關節活動度以及肌肉力量
Slowly let some limbs move
慢慢的讓一些肢體運動的功能
Or after the ability of balance and proprioception has been restored
或是平衡感及本體感覺等的能力恢復後
Then we will move on to the next stage of job simulation training.
那我們才會進行下一 階段的工作模擬訓練
The main difference between work intensive
工作強化訓練與一般醫療複健的主要差別在於
Medical rehabilitation is generally known
醫療復健為一般大家所熟知的物理治療及職能治療
Then he focused on improving the pathological problems caused by injuries.
那他著重在於改善傷病後造成的病理間題為主
such as pain management, improved joint mobility
例如疼痛處理丶改善關節活動度
and general life training such as muscle strength
及肌力等一般生活訓練
Low relevance to work situation
與工作情境的相關性較低
Work-intensive training, on the other hand, is goal-oriented
而工作強化訓練則是以目標工作為導向
A job analysis will be done first
會先進行工作分析
For the part that is difficult for workers to perform work activities
針對勞工目前執行作業活動因難的部分
By simulating the tools needed for actual work
透過模擬實際工作所需之工具
Materials, Actions, and Work Steps
材料、動作以及作業步縣
Lu may have created situations and actions similar to the original work
盧可能營造出與原工作相似之情境及動作
Achieving the skills, physical fitness and behaviors
達到訓練職災勞工工作所需之技巧丶體能和行為
in addition
另外
For example we have some labor friends
例如我們有一些勞工朋友
would need assistance with job redesign
會需要職務再設計的協助
To design some suitable accessories
去設計一些適合的輔具
enhance his work efficiency
提升他的工作效能
This is where we can help
這部分也是我們能夠協助的
And for workers who are in occupational disaster
而針對無法返回原職場的職災勞工朋友
We can also switch careers with the help of career coaching assessments
我們也可以透過職業輔導評量的協助轉換職業
These resources can be used properly
那這些資源都可以妥善的來運用
Therefore, we hope that labor friends who talk about
所以我們會希望說職災的勞工朋友不要灰心
Through Functional Rehabilitation and Vocational Rehabilitation Services
透過職能複健及職業重建的各項服務
It can effectively help you return to the workplace as soon as possible
可以有效的來協助您早日返回職場
Work reinforcement is three systematic exercise training activities
工作強化是三種有系統的運動訓練活動
in a progressive manner
以漸進的方式
Increase Occupational Labor Neuromuscular
增加職災勞工神經肌內
Cardiovascular and other functions
心臟血管等方面的功能
and focus on real or simulated work
並著重於真實或模擬工作丙容
Can't be enforced after a worker's accident
針對勞工罹災後無法執行
or projects or actions that do not meet the job competency requirements
或者不符合工作能力需求的項目或動作
Intensive training
進行強化訓練
So that workers can finally return to their original
使勞工最後能回到原職場丶勝任原工作
The current location of work intensive training in Kaohsiung City
目前高雄市工作強化訓練地點
There are four main places
主要有四個地方
Welcome labor friends in need to come and consult
歡迎有需要的勞工朋友前往洽詢
Eligible
符合資格者
free training
即可免費接受訓練
Occupational Accidents
職業災害的發生
It's often what we don't like
往往都是我們每一個人都不樂見的
But when a job disaster happens
但當職災發生時候
How to protect labor rights
如何維護勞工權益
Provides referrals for occupational injuries
提供職業傷病的轉介艦定
and resource links for Career Rehabilitation Services
以及職業重建服務的資源連結
Assist in labor dispute mediation
協助勞資爭議調解
Referral to occupational disaster comfort rooms and
轉介職業災害慰間與勞工家庭功能的繼護資源
and return to work related assistance
以及重返職場相關協助
For every worker who suffers from an occupational accident
這對每一個遭受職業災害的勞工
are very important
都是非常重要的
So we are looking forward to
所以我們非常期盼
through the Occupational Safety and Health Administration
透過職業安全衛生署辦理的
Active Service Plan for Occupational Accident Worker Cases
職災勞工個案主動服務計畫
Professionally trained occupational disaster managers
經由受過專業訓練的職災個管員
Come and refer our labor friends
來轉介我們勞工朋友
More diversified and multi-faceted services
更多元化丶多面向的服務
Assist more workers with occupational disasters
協助更多的職災勞工早日重返職場
Every occupational accident worker
每一位職業災害勞工的身上
They all have a story of their own and their destiny.
都有一個屬於他們自身與命運拼博的故事
so many labor laws
勞動法令如此多
In the end occupational accident workers can
到底職災勞工可從事業單位
What is covered by employer or labor insurance, etc.
雇主或勞工保險等獲得什麼保障
Kaohsiung City Government Labor Bureau for assistance
高雄市政府勞工局為協助
A worker friend who suffered an occupational accident
遭遇職災的勞工朋友
Simple and fast airing of self-rights
簡單快速的晾解自身權益
Filming a series of occupational accident workers rights videos
拍攝一系列職災勞工權益影片
It is hoped that in an easy-to-understand way,
希望籍由淺顯易懂方式讓民眾面臨職災時
Be able to know how to fight for relevant labor rights spillovers
能夠知道如何爭取相關的勞動權溢
so-called occupational disaster
所謂的職業災害
refers to the labor caused by the workplace
是指勞工因勞動場所
Work activities and other reasons for performing duties
作業活動及其他因執行職務的原因
Including commuting and public travel
包含上下班及公出途中
resulting illness, injury, disability or death
所引起的疾病丶傷害、失能或死亡
Classification of occupational hazards
職業災害的分類
- Occupational injury in the course of performing duties
一執行職務相關的過程中所發生的職業傷害
2. Risk factors of long-term exposure to work
二長期暴露於工作中之危險因子
causally related to the injury
與傷病具有相當因果關條
leading to occupational diseases
進而導致職業疾病
You can apply for an occupational disease ship through
可透過職業傷病防治中心申請職業病艦定
Occupational Accidents
職業災害的發生
not only cause financial loss
不僅是造成經濟上的損失
It can also cause physical or mental health problems
同時也會造成職災勞工身體或心理健康問題
lead to the inability to use their pre-injury productivity and work ability
導致無法發揮其傷病前的生產力及工作能力
even unemployment
甚至於發生失業的問題
And then derived many family economic difficulties
進而衍生出許多家庭經濟因難
and social readjustment
以及社會再適應的問題
therefore
因此
How to Plan Medical Care for Occupational Accident Workers
如何有計畫的針對職災勞工進行醫療關懷
and provide appropriate resumption arrangements
並提供適當的複工安排
Undoubtedly an important topic after occupational disasters
無疑是職業災害後的重要議題
Generally speaking
一般來說
When our Occupational Accident Worker Treatment stabilizes
當我們的職災勞工治療穩定後
can begin to enter the so-called recovery phase
就可以開始進入所謂的復工階段
The focus of management at this time will be on
此時的管理的重點會在於在復工前的準備和復工安排
In order to grasp the post-illness situation of different
以掌握不同傷病的症後情形及複工可能面對的風險
So there will be a career rebuilding program at this time.
所以此時會有職業重建計畫的介入
Include career coaching assessments
包括職業輔導評量
Psychological counselling and social adaptation
心理輔導及社會適應
Job Intensive Training, Job Redesign
工作強化訓練丶職務再設計
Vocational training, employment services, etc.
職業訓練丶就業服務等等
Whole-person assessment and training of
經由生理丶心理丶社會功能之全人評估和訓練
Assist workers to return to work
協助勞工進行複工
also
此外
Career rebuilding plans can be developed and executed by case management
職業重建計畫可以由個案管理擬定和執行
Links to related resources
也可以聯結相關資源
Assisting workers with employment
協助勞工就業
I am currently in charge of warehouse inventory in the company
我現在在公司是負責倉儲庫存的工作
When I first joined the company
一開始進來公司時
Originally, it was the job of sealing film packaging.
原本是做封膜包裝的作業
But there was an accident
但有一次意外中
My right hand was covered by the film sealer
我的右手被封膜機包覆到
The result was severe burns throughout
結果整個重度燒傷
After several times of skin grafting and stretching
後來經過了好幾次的植皮丶拉筋
Rehabilitation and Muscle Transplantation
復健還有肌肉的移植
The recovery situation will gradually stabilize
恢復狀況就有慢慢的穩定
But my right hand is so flat that it is difficult to hold and grasp it.
但是我的右手幾平很難再去握丶抓
or anything slightly heavier
或任何稍微有重量的東西了
I was really anxious
我那時候其實非常焦慮
Because there is no way to do the original sealing work.
因為根本沒有辦法再做原本的封膜工作
Fortunately, a manager later referred me to
還好後來個管員有轉介我到
Kaohsiung City Government Labor Bureau Fraternity Skills Training Center
高雄市政府勞工局博愛技能訓練中心
Finally, he helped me formulate a career coaching assessment plan
最後有幫我擬定了職業輔導評量計畫
According to the content of the plan
依據計畫的內容
It is suggested that I can consider trying the
建議我可以考量往電腦行政文書的工作表嘗試
The part about burns and scald workers' friends
關於燒燙傷職災勞工朋友的部分
Usually in the process of resumption of work, there
通常在複工的過程中有幾個重要的地方需要來觀察
The first is because the burn affects the function of sweating
第一個就是因為燒傷影響了排汗的功能
So can you adapt to the work environment?
所以在工作環境上是不是能夠適應
The second is limb function and angle, etc.
第二個就是肢體功能及角度等等
Is it possible to start working
是不是能夠開始工作
the missing part
那不足的部分
In addition to general medical rehabilitation
除一般醫療復健
Is there any kind of aid that can help him
有沒有什應樣的輔具可以來幫助他
such as hand grasping aids
例如手部抓握的輔具
Computer homework can use trackball, mouse, keypad, etc.
電腦作業的工作可以運用軌跡球滑鼠丶小鍵盤等等
These are all services that can be redesigned by job
那這些都可以籍由職務再設計的服務
To help our labor friends return to work smoothly
來幫助我們的勞工朋友順利複工
simply put
簡單來說
Job redesign services can assist
職務再設計的服務可以協助
Our Occupational Worker Friends Redesign Workflow
我們的職災勞工朋友重新來規劃工作流程
Working with employers to redesign work environment
與雇主共同的來計論工作環境的重新設計
and provide technical aids, etc.
以及提供科技輔具等等
Find a better way to work
找到更適合的工作方式
To provide workers with occupational disasters in a case-managed manner
為了以個案管理方式提供職災勞工
Personalized in-depth service
個別化的深度服務
Kaohsiung City Government Labor Bureau
高雄市政府勞工局配合勞動部推動
Active Service Program for Occupational Accident Labor Cases
職業災害勞工個案主動服務計畫
And has a single service window to return to the head office
並設有單一服務窗回專總
Take the initiative to care about and contact workers in occupational disasters
主動來關心聯繫職災勞工
For workers who have obtained a disability certificate due to occupational accident
而對於因職災而領有身心障礙證明的勞工朋友
can be referred to the Kaohsiung City Government
則可轉介至高雄市政府勞工局博愛按能訓練中心
Assisted by a central counsellor in your career coaching assessment
由中心輔導員協助您進行職業輔導評量
Vocational training, job redesign, employment services
職業訓練、職務再設計、就業服務
and entrepreneurial counseling and other related resources
以及創業輔導等相關資源
return to work early
早日重返職場
In fact, the process is from complaining to anxiety
其實那段過程就是從怨天尤人到焦慮
Then start to regain your confidence
然後再開始重新找回信心
And Kaohsiung City Government Labor Bureau
而高雄市政府勞工局的個管員
Talk to the counselors of the training center
跟博訓中心的輔導員
Helped me a lot in the process and also assisted me in
在這過程中幫助了我很多也協助我申請職務再設計的輔具
Allow me to develop smoothly into computer paperwork
讓我能順利的往電腦文書的工作上發展
Finally with the assistance of employment services
最後經過就業服務的協助
Found my current company
找到了我現在這間公司
I've been in this new company for two years now
現在我到這間新公司已經二年了
Engaged in the related work of warehouse document management
從事的就是倉儲文書管理的相關工作
I also get along very well with my colleagues here.
那跟這裡的同事也都相處得很融治
So I want to tell friends who have the same occupational accident
所以我想跟有相同發生職災的朋友說
do not give up
不要放棄
Come to the Labour Office for help
來勞工局尋求幫助
We can go back to work
我們可以重新返回職場
restart our life
重新開始我們的人生
We know very well when a worker who has an accident has to return to the workplace
我們很能了解職災勞工要重回原職場時
The situation and mood that may be encountered, etc.
可能會遇到的狀況跟心情等等
Therefore, in the preparation process before the resumption of work
所以在複工前的準備過程中
Professional service resources available for job redesign
都可以利用職務再設計的專業服務資源
Let's think about it together
一起來思考看看
For example, adjusting working methods
例如調整工作方法
Adjust or simplify work
調整或是簡化工作丙容
Improvements to the workplace environment, work equipment or machinery
改善職場環境、工作設備或機具的改良
Or provide customized technical aids, etc.
或是提供客製化的科技輔具等等
There are many ways to help
很多的方式都可以來協助
Our Occupational Accident Workers Are Better at Work
我們職災勞工在工作上更順利
Then Taiwan's Occupational Accident Labor Protection Law
那我們台灣的職業災害勞工保護法
A portion of the Auxiliary Facilities Grant is also provided
也提供了輔助設施補助的部分
There are also resources related to career services
另外也有就業服務的相關資源
can be put to good use
都可以來善加的利用
I believe it can make the process of returning to work smoother for us
相信可以讓我們重返職場的過程更順利
The resumption of work by accident workers is an
職災勞工復工是目前合灣推動的一項重要勞工政策
Help workers with occupational disasters to return to work early
幫助職災勞工早期複工
It can effectively prevent the deterioration
可以有效的來預防勞工本身的健康惡化
But so-called medical stability is not medical finality
但是所謂的醫療穩定立非醫療終正
after the medical acute phase
在醫療急性階段之後
A return to work strategy designed with the
配合職災勞工能力所設計的複工策略
Can still return to work and be productive
仍可以複工發揮生產力
Body of Workers Accident
對職災勞工之身體
Both psychological and social functioning are helpful
心理和社會功能都有助益
But the return-to-work strategy is an inter-school
但是復工策略是一門學間
Risk assessment for safe return to work
安全複工的風險評估
Need to know and understand about injuries, labor and duties
需要對傷病丶勞工和職務都了解丶認識
To prevent the injury from happening again
方能避免傷害再次發生
cause recovery failure
造成複工失敗
Now, the workers in Taiwan who have been injured at work have returned to work.
那目前台灣在職災勞工復工的
Preliminary experience and models for career reconstruction
職業重建已有初步經驗和模型
This is for the worker friend of the occupational accident
這對職災的勞工朋友來說
This represents a professional and managerial approach
這代表著一種專業和管理方式
Come and help our disaster workers return to the workplace efficiently
來有效率的幫助我們的職災勞工重返職場
Friends of non-disabled workers in occupational accident
非身心障礙的職災勞工朋友
If you have employment collusion needs
如您有就業謀合的需求
In addition to contacting the Kaohsiung City Government Labor
除了洽詢高雄市政府勞工局 職災單一服務窗口外
You can also contact the nearest person to whom the labor bureau belongs.
也可就近親洽勞工局名區所屬之
Employment service stations and service desks to
就業服務站及服務台洽詢相關就業服務資源